In this next set of videos,
在接下来的一系列视频中
I'd like to tell you about
我将向大家介绍
a problem called Anomaly Detection.
异常检测(Anomaly detection)问题
This is a reasonably commonly
这是机器学习算法
use you type machine learning.
的一个常见应用
And one of the interesting aspects
这种算法的一个有趣之处在于
is that it's mainly for
它虽然主要用于
unsupervised problem, that there's some
非监督学习问题
aspects of it that are
但从某些角度看
also very similar to sort of the supervised learning problem.
它又类似于一些监督学习问题
So, what is anomaly detection?
那么 什么是异常检测呢？
To explain it. Let me use
为了解释这个概念
the motivating example of: Imagine
让我举一个例子吧
that you're a manufacturer of
假想你是一个
aircraft engines, and let's
飞机引擎制造商
say that as your aircraft
当你生产的飞机引擎
engines roll off the assembly
从生产线上流出时
line, you're doing, you know, QA or
你需要进行
quality assurance testing, and as
QA (质量控制测试)
part of that testing you
而作为这个测试的一部分
measure features of your
你测量了飞机引擎的一些特征变量
aircraft engine, like maybe, you measure
比如 你可能测量了
the heat generated, things like
引擎运转时产生的热量
the vibrations and so on.
或者引擎的振动等等
I share some friends that worked
我有一些朋友
on this problem a long time
很早之前就开始进行这类工作
ago, and these were actually the
在实际工作中
sorts of features that they were
他们确实会从真实的飞机引擎
collecting off actual aircraft
采集这些特征变量
engines so you
这样一来
now have a data set of
你就有了一个数据集
X1 through Xm, if you have
从x(1)到x(m)
manufactured m aircraft engines,
如果你生产了m个引擎的话
and if you plot your data, maybe it looks like this.
也许你会将这些数据绘制成图表 看起来就是这个样子
So, each point here, each cross
这里的每个点 每个叉
here as one of your unlabeled examples.
都是你的无标签数据
So, the anomaly detection problem is the following.
这样 异常检测问题可以定义如下
Let's say that on, you
我们假设
know, the next day, you
后来有一天
have a new aircraft engine
你有一个新的飞机引擎
that rolls off the assembly line
从生产线上流出
and your new aircraft engine has
而你的新飞机引擎
some set of features x-test.
有特征变量x-test
What the anomaly detection problem is,
所谓的异常检测问题就是
we want to know if this
我们希望知道
aircraft engine is anomalous in
这个新的飞机引擎是否有某种异常
any way, in other words, we want
或者说
to know if, maybe, this engine
我们希望判断
should undergo further testing
这个引擎是否需要进一步测试
because, or if it looks
因为 如果它看起来
like an okay engine, and
像一个正常的引擎
so it's okay to just ship
那么我们可以直接将它运送到客户那里
it to a customer without further testing.
而不需要进一步的测试
So, if your new
比如说
aircraft engine looks like
如果你的新引擎
a point over there, well, you
对应的点落在这里
know, that looks a lot
那么 你可以认为
like the aircraft engines we've seen
它看起来像我们之前见过的引擎
before, and so maybe we'll say that it looks okay.
因此我们可以直接认为它是正常的
Whereas, if your new aircraft
然而 如果你的新飞机引擎
engine, if x-test, you know, were
如果x-test
a point that were out here,
对应的点在这外面
so that if X1 and
这里x1和
X2 are the features of this new example.
x2是这个新引擎对应的特征变量
If x-tests were all the
如果x-test在外面这么远的地方
way out there, then we would call that an anomaly.
那么我们可以认为这是一个异常
and maybe send that aircraft engine
也许我们需要在向客户发货之前
for further testing before we
进一步检测
ship it to a customer, since
这个引擎
it looks very different than
因为它和我们之前见过的
the rest of the aircraft engines we've seen before.
其他飞机引擎看起来不一样
More formally in the anomaly
如果更正式的定义
detection problem, we're give
异常检测问题
some data sets, x1 through
那么我们有一些数据
Xm of examples, and we
从x(1)到x(m)
usually assume that these end
我们通常假定这m个样本
examples are normal or
都是正常的
non-anomalous examples, and we
或者说都不是异常的
want an algorithm to tell us
然后我们需要一个算法来告诉我们
if some new example x-test is anomalous.
一个新的样本数据x-test是否是异常
The approach that we're going
我们要采取的方法是
to take is that given this training
给定训练集
set, given the unlabeled training
给定无标签的训练集
set, we're going to
我们将
build a model for p of
对数据建一个模型p(x)
x. In other words, we're
也就是说
going to build a model for the
我们将对
probability of x, where
x的分布概率建模
x are these features of, say, aircraft engines.
其中x是这些特征变量 例如飞机引擎
And so, having built a
因此 当我们
model of the probability of x
建立了x的概率模型之后
we're then going to say that
我们就会说
for the new aircraft engine, if
对于新的飞机引擎
p of x-test is less
也就是x-test 如果概率p
than some epsilon then
低于阈值ε
we flag this as an anomaly.
那么就将其标记为异常
So we see a new engine
因此当我们看到一个新的引擎
that, you know, has very low probability
在我们根据训练数据
under a model p of
得到的p(x)模型中
x that we estimate from the data,
概率非常低时
then we flag this anomaly, whereas
我们就将其标记为异常
if p of x-test is, say,
反之 如果x-test的概率p
greater than or equal to some small threshold.
大于给定的阈值ε
Then we say that, you know, okay, it looks okay.
我们就认为它是正常的
And so, given the training set,
因此 给定图中的
like that plotted here, if
这个训练集
you build a model, hopefully
如果你建立了一个模型
you will find that aircraft engines,
你将很可能发现飞机引擎
or hopefully the model p of
很可能发现模型p(x)
x will say that points that
将会认为
lie, you know, somewhere in the
在中心区域的这些点
middle, that's pretty high probability,
有很大的概率值
whereas points a little bit further out have lower probability.
而稍微远离中心区域的点概率会小一些
Points that are even further out
更远的地方的点
have somewhat lower probability, and the
它们的概率将更小
point that's way out here,
这外面的点
the point that's way
和这外面的点
out there, would be an anomaly.
将成为异常点
Whereas the point that's way in
而这边的点
there, right in the
正好在中心区域的点
middle, this would be
这些点将是正常的
okay because p of x
因为在中心区域
right in the middle of that
p(x)概率值
would be very high cause we've
会非常大
seen a lot of points in that region.
因为我们看到很多点都落在了这个区域
Here are some examples of applications of anomaly detection.
异常检测算法有如下应用案例
Perhaps the most common application of
也许异常检测
anomaly detection is actually
最常见的应用是
for detection if you
是欺诈检测
have many users, and if
假设你有很多用户
each of your users take different
你的每个用户
activities, you know maybe
都在从事不同的活动
on your website or in the
也许是在你的网站上
physical plant or something, you
也许是在一个实体工厂之类的地方
can compute features of the different users activities.
你可以对不同的用户活动计算特征变量
And what you can do is build
然后 你可以
a model to say, you know,
建立一个模型
what is the probability of different
用来表示用户表现出
users behaving different ways.
各种行为的可能性
What is the probability of a particular vector
用来表示用户行为
of features of a
对应的特征向量
users behavior so you
出现的概率
know examples of features of
因此 你看到
a users activity may be on
某个用户在网站上行为
the website it'd be things like,
的特征变量是这样的
maybe x1 is how often does
也许x1是用户登陆的频率
this user log in, x2, you know, maybe
x2也许是
the number of what
用户访问
pages visited, or the
某个页面的次数
number of transactions, maybe x3
或者交易次数
is, you know, the number of
也许x3是
posts of the users on the
用户在论坛上发贴的次数
forum, feature x4 could
x4是
be what is the typing
用户的
speed of the user and some
打字速度
websites can actually track that
有些网站是可以记录
was the typing speed of this
用户每秒
user in characters per second.
打了多少个字母的
And so you can model p of x based on this sort of data.
因此你可以根据这些数据建一个模型p(x)
And finally having your model
最后你将得到
p of x, you can
你的模型p(x)
try to identify users that
然后你可以用它来发现
are behaving very strangely on your
你网站上的行为奇怪的用户
website by checking which ones have
你只需要
probably effects less than epsilon and
看哪些用户的p(x)概率小于ε
maybe send the profiles of those users for further review.
接下来 你拿来这些用户的档案 做进一步筛选
Or demand additional identification from
或者要求这些用户
those users, or some such
验证他们的身份
to guard against you know,
从而让你的网站防御
strange behavior or fraudulent behavior on your website.
异常行为或者欺诈行为
This sort of technique will tend
这样的技术将会找到
of flag the users that are
行为不寻常的用户
behaving unusually, not just
而不只是
users that maybe behaving fraudulently.
有欺诈行为的用户
So not just constantly having
也不只是那些
stolen or users that are
被盗号的用户
trying to do funny things, or just find unusual users.
或者有滑稽行为的用户 而是行为不寻常的用户
But this is actually the technique
然而这就是许多
that is used by many online
许多在线购物网站
websites that sell things to
常用来识别异常用户
try identify users behaving
的技术
strangely that might be
这些用户行为奇怪
indicative of either fraudulent
可能是表示他们有欺诈行为
behavior or of computer accounts that have been stolen.
或者是被盗号
Another example of anomaly detection is manufacturing.
异常检测的另一个例子是在工业生产领域
So, already talked about the
事实上 我们之前已经谈到过
aircraft engine thing where you can
飞机引擎的问题
find unusual, say, aircraft
你可以找到异常的飞机引擎
engines and send those for further review.
然后要求进一步细查这些引擎的质量
A third application would be
第三个应用是
monitoring computers in a data center.
数据中心的计算机监控
I actually have some friends who work on this too.
实际上 我有些朋友正在从事这类工作
So if you have a lot
如果你管理一个
of machines in a computer
计算机集群
cluster or in a
或者一个数据中心
data center, we can do
其中有许多计算机
things like compute features at each machine.
那么我们可以为每台计算机计算特征变量
So maybe some features capturing
也许某些特征衡量
you know, how much memory used, number of
计算机的内存消耗
disc accesses, CPU load.
或者硬盘访问量 CPU负载
As well as more complex features
或者一些更加复杂的特征
like what is the CPU
例如一台计算机的
load on this machine divided by
CPU负载
the amount of network traffic
与网络流量
on this machine?
的比值
Then given the dataset of how
那么 给定正常情况下
your computers in your data
数据中心中计算机
center usually behave, you can
的特征变量
model the probability of x,
你可以建立p(x)模型
so you can model the probability
也就是说 你可以建模
of these machines having
这些计算机
different amounts of memory use
出现不同内存消耗的概率
or probability of these machines having
或者出现不同硬盘访问量
different numbers of disc accesses
的概率
or different CPU loads and so on.
或者不同的CPU负载等等
And if you ever have a machine
然后 如果你有一个计算机
whose probability of x,
它的概率p(x)
p of x, is very small then you
非常小
know that machine is behaving unusually
那么你可以认为这个计算机运行不正常
and maybe that machine is
或许它
about to go down, and you
即将停机
can flag that for review by a system administrator.
因此你可以要求系统管理员查看其工作状况
And this is actually being used
目前 这种技术
today by various data
实际正在被各大数据中心使用
centers to watch out for unusual
用来监测
things happening on their machines.
大量计算机可能发生的异常
So, that's anomaly detection.
好啦 这就是异常检测算法
In the next video, I'll
在下一个视频中
talk a bit about the Gaussian distribution and
我们将介绍一下高斯分布
review properties of the Gaussian
回顾一下高斯分布
probability distribution, and in
的一些特征
videos after that, we will
在再下一个视频中
apply it to develop an anomaly detection algorithm.
我们将利用高斯分布来推导一个异常检测算法 【教育无边界字幕组】翻译:王祖超 校对/审核: 所罗门捷列夫